<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>EECS Society</title><link href="http://eecs.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://eecs.io/feeds/anonymity.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://eecs.io/</id><updated>2014-03-27T18:00:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>Anonymity</title><link href="http://eecs.io/anonymity.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-03-27T18:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Anish Patel</name></author><id>tag:eecs.io,2014-03-27:anonymity.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As the world makes a shift online, from our daily habits increasing our reliance
on the internet here is an interesting topic that comes up, the aspect of online
anonymity. Anonymous apps such as Whisper and Secret have made us aware of the
issues we face in the modern world, reigniting the debate as to whether
anonynmity outweights the risk it comes with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an important topic beyond tech, a question of how humans should treat one
another: Can we improve ourselves? Do we want to? Do we have a moral obligation
to do so? People in tech are outstanding at building, but at moderating? There
we don’t have much of a track record. Even the likes of Facebook have not been
able to control that and make favourable decisions most of the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People are people, and will exhibit bad behaviour almost anywhere so it's more
of an individual choice. We have soldiers in Afghanistan, who might not have
proper resources to get the emotional support they need during combat. This
platform act as a medium to express feelings. Anonymity facilitates the
feeling of &amp;quot;I'm not the only one out there...&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like any other platform there are bound to be issues which we have no control
over, such systems will always get users. But to what end, and at what cost.
Sometimes it depends individually such that our personality defines who we
really are and what we end up doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We all have a story to share, and most of the times we learn from our mistakes
but I believe we can learn from other people's mistakes too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The facts are laid out but I think it's all about making the right choice by
figuring out if the positive aspects of this ideas outweigh the negative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those who'd like to give it a try, you can visit &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.secret.ly"&gt;Secret&lt;/a&gt;
or &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://whisper.sh"&gt;Whisper&lt;/a&gt; to get a better understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="apps"></category><category term="anonymity"></category></entry></feed>