<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>EECS Society</title><link href="http://eecs.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://eecs.io/feeds/blog.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://eecs.io/</id><updated>2014-10-09T23:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Meet and Greet</title><link href="http://eecs.io/meet-and-greet.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-10-09T23:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Henrik O. Skogmo</name></author><id>tag:eecs.io,2014-10-09:meet-and-greet.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;To celebrate our very first socity meeting we gave free drinks and pizza to all
attendees. We got to know some really cool people, and a lot of you were 1st
Year students. We welcome you to our great campus!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="id1"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Meet and Greet&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a tradition for all societies to have a meet and greet event in the start
of the year. But this was not only a meet and greet for us. This was our very
first official meeting. And seeing it go so well and to have students we have
never met before walk in that door and say they are here for the EECS Society
makes me proud. I am glad to see that there are other students that want a
society like this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want to create an awesome community where we all can have fun and learn from
each other. To do so we need to talk to you to know what you guys want. And that
was what this evening was all about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are planning a programming competition for our next event. If you have ever
heard about &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://robocode.sourceforge.net/"&gt;Robocode&lt;/a&gt;, then you might take a look into it ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks everyone for showing up! Follow our &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://twitter.com/eecssoc"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://facebook.com/groups/eecssoc"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; for more
information about events and the society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can contribute with technical articles in our &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/qmcs/qmcs.github.io"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; repo. We have made a
guide there for you to follow. Also you can check the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/qmcs/qmcs.github.io/issues"&gt;issues&lt;/a&gt; section to read
and comment on projects and events for consideration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><category term="social"></category><category term="meeting"></category></entry></feed>