<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>EECS Society</title><link href="http://eecs.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://eecs.io/feeds/interview.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://eecs.io/</id><updated>2016-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>James and Uche</title><link href="http://eecs.io/james-and-uche.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Dmitrijs Milajevs</name></author><id>tag:eecs.io,2016-01-28:james-and-uche.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="who-are-you-and-what-are-you-doing"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Who are you and what are you doing?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are James and Uche. Together we founded &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://yapnak.com/"&gt;Yapnak&lt;/a&gt;; the lunch app that brings
students exclusive lunch deals for £5 and no hassle. Funnily enough, we're not
tech guys (background wise) but instead both final year &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.smd.qmul.ac.uk/"&gt;Queen Mary medical
students&lt;/a&gt;. However, we love food and so Yapnak was
born. When we're not being student doctors we're working on Yapnak and trying to
create the best possible food service that students can have. With over 500
downloads and 100 claims in a few weeks we're actively trying to fan the flame.
We've managed to getsign up some of the trendier restaurants around like
Tayyabs, Greedy Cow and even our very own Drapers! If you haven't heard of us or
seen the app check it out via our web link www.yapnak.com.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="what-do-you-expect-from-a-recent-graduate-to-become-a-successful-member-of-your-team"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What do you expect from a recent graduate to become a successful member of your team?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's a good question. Three things spring to mind. Creativity, an infectious
personality, and a strong work ethic. At this stage we're looking for people who
can buy in to the ambition of our group, but don't need much motivation to get
going. It's always nice to have someone who can bring something a little
different to the team; of course that can vary from person to person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="how-did-you-learn-programming"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How did you learn programming?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simple answer to that question is we didn't! We have surrounded ourselves
with the right people and looked for those with skills that complement us. Enter
our CTO, Joshua. We needed a smart and personable tech person on the team and
when we identified him we brought him on board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><category term="interview"></category></entry><entry><title>Alexandre González</title><link href="http://eecs.io/alexandre-gonzalez.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-03-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Dmitrijs Milajevs</name></author><id>tag:eecs.io,2015-03-09:alexandre-gonzalez.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Who are you and what are you doing?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My name is Álex González (&lt;a href="http://twitter.com/agonzalezro"&gt;@agonzalezro&lt;/a&gt; on
twitter) and what I do in my day to day basis is programming in
&lt;a href="https://golang.org/"&gt;Go&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://rubyonrails.org/"&gt;RoR&lt;/a&gt; (mainly Go) plus some
devops work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am currently working at &lt;a href="http://shopa.com"&gt;Shopa&lt;/a&gt; which is "where shopping
gets social, connecting retailers with customers through the power of
recommendation" (see &lt;a href="http://techcrunch.com/2015/02/17/social-shopping-app-shopa-secures-11m-series-a-to-scale-internationally/"&gt;an article on Techcrunch&lt;/a&gt;
about us) which mainly means that we give you money if you refer people to buy
products that we have in catalog. It's quite cool that you can create and share
your own collections though, if you are into the fashion world, you must try it.
And if you are not, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What do you expect from a recent graduate to become a successful member of your team?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mainly attitude. If you are a recent graduate I don't expect you to be a crack.
I hate when somebody tries to show me that they know stuff about something that
they really don't know. Don't be that person!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will be at the beginning of your practical learning process and, as I said,
your attitude is the most important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I know what this question is about and I will recommend you few things
to check:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;any kind of control version system, you can start with
  &lt;a href="http://git-scm.com/"&gt;git&lt;/a&gt;. It's cool to name your projects: &lt;code&gt;_final&lt;/code&gt;,
  &lt;code&gt;_final_final&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;_final_v2_this_time_is_true&lt;/code&gt;; but trust me, it stops being fun
  with the time. I would like that somebody explained me that at the first year
  of the university.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;learn some language that is not covered at the university. I am pretty sure that
  some of your teachers told you: if you know how to develop on X, you know how
  to develop on Y, but... this sentence have some caveats. My recommendations
  (not subjective at all) are Go and &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/"&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;master your editor, whatever it is, this is not a war between
  &lt;a href="http://www.vim.org/"&gt;vim&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/"&gt;emacs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;do you know what is unit testing? You should start learning it and it will
  help you A LOT now and in the future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;we have &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Object-relational_mapping"&gt;ORMs&lt;/a&gt; that
  makes the data layers of your programs extremely simple, but knowing some
  &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SQL"&gt;SQL&lt;/a&gt; to understand what those ORMs do in the
  background would be helpful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;learning some &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NoSQL"&gt;NoSQL&lt;/a&gt; as well will be a
  good addition to your toolbox.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;grab some Open Source project that you like and try to understand its
  internals. This will help you to get comfortable reading others people source
  code which is going to be extremely useful in the future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am pretty sure that I am missing some important point, the points I mentioned
require quite a lot of time to master. If you finish them all, feel free to ask
me where to do further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How did you learn programming?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My dad had some &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amstrad_CPC"&gt;Amstrad CPC&lt;/a&gt;
magazines explaining the basics of Basic around the house so I got interested
about knowing what were those weird characters in the magazine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the age of ~14(?) I made my first program. My father is an electrician and
he had a book explaining the number of heaters needed by a house depending
where they live, size of the house, etc... I made it with Basic by
copy/pasting (back then, I didn't even know what a function was). When I
finished it, I had the first bad experience with programming: I was a so-so
result of what I achieved, but my father asked me "where are the icons?". So,
in that exact point I realised that 1) UI is important &amp;amp; 2) nobody cares about
the details of what you have done, they want the beautiful chassis and that it
starts when you turn the key.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="interview"></category><category term="go"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="git"></category></entry></feed>