<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Computing</title><link href="http://pyclub.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://pyclub.github.io/feeds/opportunities.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://pyclub.github.io/</id><updated>2014-02-28T19:32:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>Facebook Hackathon</title><link href="http://pyclub.github.io/facebook-hackathon.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-02-28T19:32:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Umar Qureshi</name></author><id>tag:pyclub.github.io,2014-02-28:facebook-hackathon.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you havent heard yet, Facebook will be hosting a Hackathon on Saturday, 15
March 2014. A Hackathon is a (codefest) event where computer programmers and
others involved in software development, graphic designers, interface
designers and project managers collaborate intensively on software
projects.Hackathons tend to have a specific focus, which can include the
programming language used, the operating, an application, an API, or the
subject and the demographic group of the programmer. Though for the Facebook
hackthon, there isnt any restriction on what you can make so aim for the sky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So Join Facebook in London as we stay up all night hacking, learning and
having a some fun! Start brainstorming ideas &amp;amp; forming teams (of up to 4
people). Facebook will suply us with  food, fun diversions, prizes, and some
expert guidance in the form of our engineers. Travel will be reimbursed for
public transportation.You bring your laptop, appetite, skills and ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The winning team will get the chance to compete against teams from other
Hackathons both domestically and internationally at the Hackathon Finals and
be judged by Facebook executives -- held at Facebook HQ in Menlo Park,
California in November!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a link for registration
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.surveymonkey.com/s/londonhackathon"&gt;https://www.surveymonkey.com/s/londonhackathon&lt;/a&gt;. Register before the 4th of
March. The event is over subscribed but you can still apply. Be ready for a
coding puzzle on the 4th of March, this will be your ticket to the event.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="Facebook"></category></entry><entry><title>GSOC project: MoinMoin</title><link href="http://pyclub.github.io/gsoc-project-moinmoin.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-02-10T11:17:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Dmitrijs Milajevs</name></author><id>tag:pyclub.github.io,2014-02-10:gsoc-project-moinmoin.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://moinmo.in/"&gt;MoinMoin&lt;/a&gt;, a wiki engine, published &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://moinmo.in/GoogleSoc2014/InitialProjectIdeas"&gt;initial project ideas&lt;/a&gt; for the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.google-melange.com/gsoc/homepage/google/gsoc2014"&gt;Google
Summer of Code 2014&lt;/a&gt;. MoinMoin is a mature project with a wonderful core team.
They participated in GSOC for many years.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="gsoc"></category></entry><entry><title>QCon London</title><link href="http://pyclub.github.io/qcon-london.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-31T17:42:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Dmitrijs Milajevs</name></author><id>tag:pyclub.github.io,2014-01-31:qcon-london.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://qconlondon.com/"&gt;QCon London&lt;/a&gt; is looking for students to volunteer.
Get more details and fill in the application form &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://qconlondon.com/london-2014/crew/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="conference"></category><category term="scholarship"></category></entry><entry><title>PyData, Europython and Google</title><link href="http://pyclub.github.io/pydata-europython-and-google.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-29T09:03:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Dmitrijs Milajevs</name></author><id>tag:pyclub.github.io,2014-01-29:pydata-europython-and-google.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are several events on the radar that not only give you loads of
knowledge, but also give you some money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="pydata-in-london"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;PyData in London&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://pydata.org/ldn2014"&gt;PyData&lt;/a&gt; is a conference dedicated to the scientific tools in Python. London is
the first city outside the U.S. that hosts the conference on February 21 - 23.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time several &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://pydata.org/ldn2014/news/"&gt;diversity scholarships&lt;/a&gt; are offered. Here is the
announcement from the conference page:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the goals of PyData is to increase awareness and excitement around
opportunities for women and underrepresented groups in software engineering.
To increase diversity in scientific computing, our outreach programmes range
from hosting workshops to introduce programming to young women, to encouraging
diversity in speakers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For PyData London 2014, we are offering scholarship opportunities to women and
those from other underrepresented groups who may otherwise be unable to attend
the conference. Generous donations from the Python Software Foundation and
NumFocus have made these efforts possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To apply for a scholarship, please fill out our &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1Ke-RVO09nDgZBls6zt0PDpNLRGczykRB-cRTwrRReqk/viewform"&gt;application&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go ahead and drop several lines!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="europython-in-berlin"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Europython in Berlin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Europython is a largest Python related event in Europe. It's usually running
for a week. This year the conference will be in Berlin, Germany, on July 21 -
27.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is possible to get early bit tickets with a student discount, you just need
to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blog.europython.eu/post/74824001195/the-early-bird-ticket-sale-will-start-soon-special"&gt;send your student ID&lt;/a&gt;. Grants should be announced soon, so read their
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blog.europython.eu"&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; or follow &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/europython"&gt;&amp;#64;europython&lt;/a&gt;. See you in Berlin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="google-summer-of-code-worldwide"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Google Summer of Code worldwide&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case you didn't hear about &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.google-melange.com/gsoc/document/show/gsoc_program/google/gsoc2014/about_page"&gt;Google Summer of Code&lt;/a&gt;, it is something like
a software engineering project, but first, you do something useful, second,
you get a lot of support from professional developers (so you are not alone
trying to configure SVN and NetBeans), and you get paid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far the program is in early stage, the list of accepted projects &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.google-melange.com/gsoc/events/google/gsoc2014"&gt;will be
published on February 24&lt;/a&gt;. However, it's a good idea to go trough the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.google-melange.com/gsoc/projects/list/google/gsoc2013"&gt;project list of 2013&lt;/a&gt; to get an idea of possible projects and good
applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><category term="conference"></category><category term="scholarship"></category></entry></feed>